U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5003 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series XXIV: Southern Railway: Inman Yards and Atlanta Terminal
  - Industrial Track Crossing Haynes Street at Aristocrat Ice Cream Co (Box 58, Folder 122)
    Southern railway industrial track in downtown Atlanta. Lighted building on the right is Aristocrat Ice Cream Co. Street crossing tracks in middle of photograph has a blind approach because of surrounding buildings.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 122)
  - Looking South Towards Fair Street and Swift Packing Company (Box 58, Folder 123)
    Fair Street crosses tracks out from between the two buildings on the right. Total blind spot. Very steep grade coming up to this crossing. Vehicles and pedestrians are practically on track at right before they can be seen from an engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 123)
  - Looking North from Fair Street Toward Castleberry Street (Box 58, Folder 124)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 124)
  - Engine at North Side of Fair Street Crossing (Box 58, Folder 125)
    Note trash barrel between wall and track. This is on fire at various times and the smoke blurs signals and makes a fire hazard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 125)
  - Looking North on McDonough Street Bridge (Box 58, Folder 126)
    Site of old Roseland Depot in right background of photograph (building with colonnades along its platform). The Chevrolet plant is about three blocks south of this bridge. The track on the left s an industrial track. The next track to the right is the new third main line being put in to expedite main line traffic for the Chevrolet plant. Note the roadway machine working on this track in the background, and the one working on the new Chevrolet plant lead in the center of the photo. The two center tracks are Southern No. 1 and 2 tracks going south from Atlanta to Macon. Machine on track is on new Chevrolet plant lead.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 126)
  - Northwest Side of Chevrolet Plant (Box 58, Folder 127)
    This is an overall view of the Chevrolet Plant. The industrial tracks are all in the foreground, the main lines just beyond the fence and the plant lead is beyond the main line. All tracks on this plant lead off the lead in a sharp curve. This makes it necessary to have a fireman on the engine to relay signals to the engineer, plus four men on the ground instead of the usual three.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 127)
  - View of the Chevrolet Plant (Box 58, Folder 128)
    High voltage lines go there this area here. Shows the unloading point for oil, paint thinner, and other materials.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 128)
  - Trailers for Sale by Southern Railway (Box 58, Folder 129)
    These were formerly used by Maintenance of Way workers. There are over 200 of them.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 129)
  - Grade Crossing at Ashby Street (Box 58, Folder 130)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 130)
  - Looking West from Ashby Street Crossing Toward Jefferson Street (Box 58, Folder 131)
    Atlantic Coast line. Note curves, debris, grass, and buildings blocking line of sight.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 131)
  - Looking East from Central Avenue Bridge at Central of Georgia Tracks (Box 58, Folder 132)
    Looking towards Washington Street Bridge. Note "S" curve of tracks, close clearances, and overhead bridges.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 132)
  - Central of Georgia's Grade Crossing Under Union Station (Box 58, Folder 133)
    Note the close clearance of the columns on the right, the mail truck approaching the crossing, and the curvature of the track. These tracks go through an area like this for approximately half a mile. Buildings and street are overhead, so it is always dark, even in the daytime.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 133)
  - Looking Southsast On Belt Line at Industry Across Monroe Drive (Box 58, Folder 134)
    Note trees, poles, and weeds obscuring tracks. Heavy traffic here.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 134)
  - Looking South Off Highland Avenue Toward Belt Line (Box 58, Folder 135)
    Shows industrial area off Highland Avenue serviced by the Belt Line of the Southern Railway. Note the close clearance between cars, posts, and stacks of brick. Many men and vehicles are moving around in this area.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 135)
  - Looking South from Highland Avenue Bridge at Belt Line (Box 58, Folder 136)
    Engine is going towards Irwin Street crossing. Note curves, trees, buildings, and debris on tracks. The Belt Line services 35 industries during the day, an about the same number at night. This Belt Line runs from the east main line at Armour yard approximately 5 miles to the Decatur Street yard which joins the Atlanta Joint Terminal Yard. From Armour to Decatur, it is uphill all the way and made up of numerous curves like the ones seen in this photograph. It requires a five man crew to do the job safely.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 136)
  - Going Down Hill North on Belt Line Toward Irwin Street Crossing (Box 58, Folder 137)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 137)
  - Southern Belt Line track at Airline Street Looking North (Box 58, Folder 138)
    The Belt Line tracks are on the right and the industrial tracks on the left. Irwin Street crossing is two blocks north of the Edgewood Viaduct seen in the top right of photograph. Note curvature of tracks, support columns, and the crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 138)
  - Looking North on Belt Line Towards Decatur Street Crossing (Box 58, Folder 139)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 139)
  - Looking North from Marietta Boulevard Bridge (Box 58, Folder 140)
    L&N main lines are in the left-center of photograph. The double unit in the center is on the outbound thoroughfare used by yard engines coming from the L&N and Atlantic Coast Line Railroad yard. The track leading off to the right goes into the L&N yard. At the extreme left top is the receiving yard at Inman Yards. Note the curvature of the tracks and the steep down grade into the L&N yards.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 140)
  - Looking to South End of L&N Receiving Yard (Box 58, Folder 141)
    Where all foreign deliveries are made. Track on extreme right is Atlantic Coat Line's outbound freigth lead leaving the L&N yard. Note curves, poles, weeds, and debris on tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 141)
  - Looking to South End of L&N Receiving Yard (Box 58, Folder 142)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 142)
  - Looking South from Marietta Boulevard Bridge Across L&N Receiving and Outbound Yard (Box 58, Folder 143)
    L&N main lines to extreme right of photograph. The four right hand tracks adjacent to the main lines are forwarding tracks. Tracks on either side of coal train at left are receiving tracks. Note curves, grades, poles, and debris on tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 143)
  - Looking North from Marietta Boulevard Bridge Across L&N Yard (Box 58, Folder 144)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 144)
  - Looking South from Marietta Street Bridge at the L&N Yard and Shops (Box 58, Folder 145)
    The receiving track is on the right. the car repair tracks are by the coal chute at the right center. The engine shop is at the left center. Note curvature of tracks, blind spots, and close clearances.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 58, Folder 145)
  - Railroad Employees in Classification Yard (Box 60, Folder 35)
    (See exhibit U-23)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 60, Folder 35)
  - Recieving Yard (Box 63, Folder 167)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 167)
  - Freight Cars and Passenger Cars (Box 63, Folder 170)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 170)
- Series XXV: Southern Pacific Railroad: Los Angeles SoPac Yards
  This series consists of photographs of the Southern Pacific's facilities in Los Angeles, California. These photographs were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 99, are referred to by the letters BB, and were taken by B.J. Mahoney. There is no extant testimony for these photographs, but there are hand written notes describing their contents. The Southern Pacific was a class I railroad in the western United States. It covered a vast territory, with lines stretching from New Orleans through Texas, New Mexico and Arizona to Los Angeles; from Los Angeles up the West Coast through San Francisco and Sacramento to Portland, Oregon; from Chicago through St. Louis to Dallas and Ft. Worth, Texas; and from San Francisco through Nevada to Ogden, Utah. The Sunset Route, between New Orleans and Los Angeles, went through El Paso, Tucson and Phoenix, with a branch line heading south into Mexico at Nogales. The photographs in this series document the SP facilities in Los Angeles and a small portion of the surrounding city.
  - Looking South in the "C" Yard of the Southern Pacific Yards, SP Units No. 5239 and 1408 (Box 63, Folder 121)
    Picture shows relatively few cars for this yard and only two engines. Generally there are several engines working in this area and requires a lookout on both sides to assure safety.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 121)
  - View of the "C" Yard of the Southern Pacific Yards Looking South (Box 63, Folder 122)
    The tracks in the forefront converge to a puzzle and cars and engines can be expected to move in either direction at any time.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 122)
  - View of East Leg of Wye Heading Out on Alameda Street (Box 63, Folder 123)
    Heavy vehicular traffic and several crossings make this location hazardous at E. 27th Street.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 123)
  - East Leg of Wye at Butte Street (Box 63, Folder 124)
    Showing tracks leading into industries the curvature of which require the use of fireman.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 124)
  - View of 8th Street Yard (Box 63, Folder 125)
    Extreme curves and short clearance in this yard. Safety of all employees requires the use of fireman. SP Unit 1016
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 125)
  - Looking Across the Top of the "C" Yard (Box 63, Folder 126)
    Heavy movements of several engines in this vicinity & many employees working here. SP Unit #5270
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 126)
  - Looking North Over the Southern Pacific "B" Yard (Box 63, Folder 127)
    Many cross-overs and leads and impaired vision. Movements can be expected at any time in either direction.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 127)
  - Top End of the "C" Yard at Los Angeles (Box 63, Folder 128)
    Looking North to the "B" Yard. Leads and cross-overs make this location hazardous.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 128)
  - Looking South from the Lower End of "A" Yard (Box 63, Folder 129)
    Showing portion of hump yard and "B" yard leads. Heavy switching performed in this area.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 129)
  - Looking South into the "B" Yard as Engine is Moving Over Hump (Box 63, Folder 130)
    Cars not rolling into clear sometimes create hazard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 130)
  - Looking North into the Lower End of "C" Yard (Box 63, Folder 131)
    Where main line enters yard. Many leads and crossovers in this area.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 131)
  - View of Interlocking Plant of the L.A. U.P.T (Box 63, Folder 132)
    Many terminal employees and motor cars handling freight and mail require vigilant look out.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 132)
  - View of Signals and Tracks of the L.A. U.PT (Box 63, Folder 133)
    Movements of engines controlled by signal indication requiring use of fireman to observe signals.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 133)
  - Looking North from the Lower End of "A" Yard (Box 63, Folder 134)
    Impaired clearance and vision due to curvature. Entire yard is on grade.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 134)
  - View of Main Line Entering Los Angeles' Southern Pacific Terminal and Piggy Back Yard (Box 63, Folder 135)
    Extreme curves and grade plus multiple movements require constant lookout.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 135)
  - View of Southern Pacific's Butte Street Yard (Box 63, Folder 136)
    To the left of picture is Pacific Electric Yard and movements in all directions by either carrier can be expected at any time.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 136)
  - Overlooking "B" Yard at Los Angeles from Top of Hump Yard (Box 63, Folder 137)
    Many curves and leads in this area with several engines working here although not shown in picture require vigilant lookout.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 137)
  - Looking North from Top End of Cornfield into Lower End of Bull Ring of Southern Pacific Yards (Box 63, Folder 138)
    Entire yard on grade has created hazard of runaway cars requiring constant vigilance.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 138)
  - View of Lower End of Cornfield of Southern Pacific Yards (Box 63, Folder 139)
    Employees clean commodity cars at this location and are in and around cars requiring constant lookout.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 139)
  - View of Southern Pacific's Coach Yard (Box 63, Folder 140)
    Many non-operating employees in this area; impaired vision due to extreme curves.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 140)
  - View of Pacific Electric Yard (Box 63, Folder 141)
    21 Point of interchange with Southern Pacific Company.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 141)
  - View of Main Line Entering Los Angeles Southern Pacific Terminal & Piggy Back Yard (Box 63, Folder 142)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 142)
- Series XXVI: Southern Pacific Railroad: Western Division, West Oakland Yards
  This series consists of photographs of the Southern Pacific's facilities in Oakland, California. These photographs were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 25, are referred to by the letter R in testimony, and were taken by R. Vawter. Mr. Vawter was employed in engine service on the Western Division of the Southern Pacific Company, Pacific Lines, in the yards in Oakland, California. The West Oakland Yards were more than 30 miles long, and served the entire East Bay of the San Francisco metropolitan area. The Southern Pacific was a class I railroad in the western United States. It covered a vast territory, with lines stretching from New Orleans through Texas, New Mexico and Arizona to Los Angeles; from Los Angeles up the West Coast through San Francisco and Sacramento to Portland, Oregon; from Chicago through St. Louis to Dallas and Ft. Worth, Texas; and from San Francisco through Nevada to Ogden, Utah. The Sunset Route, between New Orleans and Los Angeles, went through El Paso, Tucson and Phoenix, with a branch line heading south into Mexico at Nogales. The photographs in this series document the SP facilities in Oakland as well as the industries it served and portions of downtown Oakland, California including the Fruitvale Cannery station, now a commuter station on the BART system.
  - Looking East Toward West Oakland Diesel Shop, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 87)
    Shows the West Oakland Diesel Shop. All switches in view are of variable type. Engines are allowed to be either headed or backed out of these tracks. Note sanding and fueling devices at sides and above. Due to clearance and type of switches a safe move there necessitates a man on each side of locomotive cab.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 87)
  - View of Engineer on Locomotive Working Forward, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 88)
    Engineer would not be able to see trucks parked on tracks or tractor in foul of tracks. The prints in this in this group (R2a-R2d) were all taken around the mail loading installation in the coach yard at West Oakland, CA.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 88)
  - Men and Equipment Cars Foul Tracks in This Area, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 89)
    The photos in this group (R2a-R2d) were taken around the mail loading installation in the coach Yard at West Oakland, CA.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 89)
  - Trucks and Equipment are Left Unattended in and Near Tracks in This Area, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 90)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 90)
  - More Unattended Equipment Left on Tracks, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 91)
    Unprotected, other than vigilance of engine and switch crews. The photos in this group (R2a- R2d) were taken around the mail loading installation in the coach yard at West Oakland, CA.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 91)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 92)
    Laborer working near tracks, no protection afforded. Equipment in foul on opposite side of track. An Engine moving on this track would need a pair of eyes on both sides of locomotive cab.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 92)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 93)
    Shows that men and equipment are working in and about these cars, and any movement may mean life or limb to them, so that a safe move here requires a close watch from both sides of a locomotive at all times. (like R-4A)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 93)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 94)
    Taken in the West Oakland coach yard as shows various maintenance work being carried on. Shows that men and equipment are working in and about these cars, and any movement may mean life or limb to them, so that a safe move here requires a close watch from both sides of a locomotive at all times.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 94)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 95)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 95)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 96)
    Shows that men and equipment are working in and about these cars, and any movement may mean life or limb to them, so that a safe move here requires a close watch from both sides of a locomotive at all times.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 96)
  - Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 97)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 97)
  - East End of Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 98)
    Was taken at the east end of the coach at West Oakland. All switches in this area of variable type. Note that engineer is blind on left side of engine, as to any movement that may be taking place on that side. Also note in this picture, an engine moving towards the switch with visible V, the engine could not see the engine approaching from the opposite direction. He must depend on the man on the left side of the cab in both cases. SP Unit 1002.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 98)
  - East End of Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 99)
    All switches in this area of variable type. Note that engineer is blind on left side of engine, as to any movement that may be taking place on that side. Also note in this picture, an engine moving towards the switch with visible V, the engine could not see the engine approaching from the opposite direction. He must depend on the man on the left side of the cab in both cases. (like R-5)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 99)
  - East End of Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 100)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 100)
  - East End of Coach Yard, West Oakland, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 101)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 101)
  - West Oakland Yard, Elmhurst Main Line Track, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 102)
    Was taken in the West Oakland yard and shows an engine and cars entering the westbound Elmhurst main line track. Movement on these track is governed by automatic block signal preceding the one visible in picture so that a movement could be made on this track even though preceding signal had been in stop position. View of any such movement could not be seen from engineers side of cab in locomotive shown in picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 102)
  - Photo Taken from Adline Street Overpass, Looking West at West Oakland Yard Proper, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 103)
    View of the Southern Pacific West Oakland Yard. Note the complex lay out of tracks, crossovers, curvature of tracks. So that switching movements here in necessitate a close look out from both sides of a switch locomotive at all times. (Bay Bridge and Treasure Island in background).
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 103)
  - Photo Taken from Adline Street Overpass, Looking West at West Oakland Yard Proper, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 104)
    Note the complex lay out of tracks, crossovers, curvature of tracks. So that switching movements here in necessitate a close look out from both sides of a switch locomotive at all times. (Bay Bridge and Treasure Island in background). (like R-7)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 104)
  - Switching at the Fruit Vale Cannery in West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 105a)
    Shows the switching operation at the Fruitvale Cannery. Note sharp curvature of track into plant and movements in and out of this plant require continued movements over busy plant crossing in. Fruitvale Station in center background of picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 105a)
  - Switching at the Fruitvale Cannery in West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 105b)
    Shows the switching operation at the Fruitvale Cannery. One man cannot be watching signals from switch crew and traffic on street crossing at the same time.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 105b)
  - Engine Running Forward with Heavy Rock Cars Loaded, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 106)
    Was taken at a location near 23rd Avenue in what is known as the East Oakland area; shows an industrial track coming from the Fruitvale area going towards 19th Avenue. For the aggregate plant shown, this track is down grade on a curve to the left; the auto in picture could not be seen for several feet from engineers side of cab.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 106)
  - Industrial Areas, West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 107)
    Shows he sharp curvature of the track into the American Can Company Plant.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 107)
  - Industrial Area and Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 108)
    Unprotected street crossing that is obscured on both sides by buildings.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 108)
  - Industrial Areas, West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 109)
    Street crossing in Eneryville, another industrial area in Oakland.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 109)
  - Industrial Areas, West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 110)
    Showing congestion of auto traffic over tracks where switching movements must be made at all times every day. Note that many places involve curve of tracks so that to be safe both sides of engine must be protected. (like R-9e)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 110)
  - Industrial Areas, West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 111)
    Another street crossing in the Oakland area and the maze of traffic and traffic signals.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 111)
  - Industrial Areas, West Oakland Yard, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 112)
    Showing congestion of auto traffic over tracks where switching movements must be made at all times every day. Note that many places involve curve of tracks so that to be safe both sides of engine must be protected.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 54, Folder 112)
  - Approach to Blind Grade Crossing, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 113)